welcome back to part three of our
three-part series with Daniel smoked a
burger on the generator function of
existential risks in this episode Daniel
shares his vision for a path towards a
post existential risk future and the
three key features of this new
civilization design he also talks about
why there is no place for incentives in
such a world to get all the links and
show notes from this episode go to
future thinkers org slash 57 you can
also find the first and second part of
this interview there this episode is
brought to you by quality at a premium a
nootropic supplement that helps support
mental performance and brain health it's
specifically designed to promote focus
support energy mental clarity mood
memory and creativity UV and I have both
used it in the past we really liked it
and we actually met the founders and
interviewed them on future thinkers and
you can check out those interviews
they're one of our favorites at future
thinkers org slash Daniel and future
thinkers org slash jordan they've got a
new formula up called qualia mind it's
got more natural ingredients and you can
get it at future thinkers org slash
brain hack and you can get 10% off if
you use the code future alright let's
get into the show
welcome to future thinkers org a podcast
about the evolution of technology
society and consciousness I'm Mike
Gilliland and I'm UV Ivanova if you new
to the show and you'd like a list of our
top episodes and resources go to future
thinkers Dyer org slash start and if you
like our podcast leave us a rating and a
review on iTunes and elsewhere
it really helps others find the show and
we really appreciate it I'm reading Carl
Jung right now and he's talking about
his experience of going to live with the
Pueblo Indians and how it completely
just blew apart his conception of what
was natural and how the Western world
view is different from other worldviews
and he noticed that they were so happy
and serene and they felt themselves as
one with their environment and they had
this very special relationship with the
Sun and it was just it was very
beautiful but at the same time he
realized how they were very vulnerable
to you know the invasion of the Western
civilization so if we create a new
civilization operating system that is
not oriented towards winning wars then
how do we ensure that it doesn't get
destroyed by those who are imagine
there's a group of people that get a
stronger theory of causation so they
learn Newton's physics and so now they
can use calculus to plot a ballistic
curve and make the cannon ball hit the
right spot every time rather than the
pendulum dowsing which is kind of a hit
or miss that belief is going to catch on
and that's why science really caught on
took us out of the Dark Ages was because
it led to better weapons and better
agriculture tech and better like real
so it proliferated because it was
proliferative if we increased our theory
of causation that ends up catching on
but if we could increase our theory of
causation and our theory of choice and
the relationship between them that would
actually be the most adaptive especially
in the presence of where a particular
game theoretic model of choice with the
extension of causation we have is
definitely self terminating definitely
anti adaptive and so I know we've been
on for a long time so there's really
only one more thing that I want to share
that kind of closes this set of concepts
so remember we said that any source of
asymmetric advantage competitive
advantage in a win-lose game will end up
once it's deployed being figured out in
utilized by everybody you just up the
level of fancy and playing field so but
we also said the Indians you were just
mentioning and many of the treasures
we've mentioned lost win lose games we
don't want to try and build something
that's just going to lose at a win-lose
game but we know that if it tries to win
at win-lose games it's just still part
of the same existential curve that we're
on so it has to not lose at a win-lose
game while also not seeking to win but
do it so it's basically not playing the
game but it is oriented about how not to
lose this is a very important thing and
so we can think about power the way we
have traditionally thought of power is a
power over or power against type dynamic
a game theoretic win-lose dynamic and
that that any agent that deploys a
particular kind of power leads to other
agents for you on how to deploy the same
and other kinds of powered power keeps
it anting up till we get to problems but
we could think about another term we
might call strength which is not the
power to beat someone else but it's the
ability to not be beat by someone else
it's the ability to maintain our own
sovereignty and our own coherence in the
presence of outside forces and so we can
talk about my power like can I go beat
somebody up but my strength is can my
body fend off viruses and can I fend off
cancers and can I actually protect
myself if I need to protect myself which
is different than can I go beat other
people up and now the power game is the
game we actually have to cure power over
dynamics mean rivalry sign AMEX mean
when loose dynamics is the source of
evil it's not that money is the source
of evil it's that power over where I
think my well-being is ante coupled to
yours ends up being the source of evil
and money's just very deep in the stack
of power dynamics but statuses and
certain ways of relating to sex and the
number of things are so we have to get
rid of the power over dynamics but it
doesn't mean that I can't develop
strength that makes me anti fragile in
the presence of rivalry and then I say
well what kind of capacity can I
developed it doesn't get weaponized by
somebody else and used against me given
that any asymmetric capacity I get can
be weaponized
there's really only one and this is a
really interesting thing
if I make the adaptive capacity of they
were trying to make a new civilization
as a model and the new full-stack
civilization new economics new
governance new infrastructure new
culture that has comprehensive loop
closure right doesn't create
accumulation or depletion doesn't have
rival risk games within it etc if I try
to have some unique adaptive capacity
via certain type of information tech the
other world will see that information
Tekken is it for all kinds of purposes
including against me where there's an
incentive to do so and the same is true
if I used military tech or if I use
environmental extraction technology the
advantage of the way the civilization
structured has to do with increased
coherence in the sense making and choice
making between all the agents in the
system all the people in the system
increase interpersonal coherence this
cannot be weaponized and anyone else
employing it is now just a system itself
propagating so for instance when we
start playing rival risk games we start
realizing that it's not just us against
somebody else it's teams against larger
teams right answer them the idea of the
team is we're supposed to cooperate with
each other to compete against somebody
else but compete against someone else
idea ends up going fractal and I end up
even competing against my teammates
sometimes and that's part of that why
the collective intelligence doesn't
scale thing is because ou cooperate with
my other buddies on the basketball team
unless there's also a thing called the
most valuable player and I'm in the
running for it and I have a chance to
make the three-point shot rather than
pass even though it decreases the chance
of the team winning now I have a
incentive misalignment so I might go for
that and then it gets bigger where
there's a couple of us that both want
the same promotion to the same position
at the company and we're actually going
to try and sabotage the other one even
though that harms the company because my
own incentive is not coupled with their
incentive and with the company and then
I can look at say a couple different
government agencies that are competing
for the same chunk of budget it will
actually seek to undermine each other so
they get more of the budget when they're
supposed to be on the same
called that country and so what we
realized as we get this thing called you
know like fractal disinformation fractal
decoherence and defection happening
everywhere and that creates the most
broken information ecology and the least
effective coordination and cooperation
possible and that's everywhere right
that's ubiquitous and it's the result of
that underlying rivalry so as we
mentioned before now if I have some
information I want to make it to where
nobody else can use it I'm gonna
trademark it patented protect my
intellectual property and before I've
released it I actually want to dis
inform everybody else about it right
tell them the gold is somewhere else so
that they go dig in someone else and
don't pay attention when I'm doing so if
I am both hoarding information dis
informing others and keeping my
information from being able to be
synthesized with others that means that
I'm going to not let my knowledge about
cancer research and whatever it is be
out there because I got to make the farm
on your back so the best computer that
the world could build doesn't exist
because Apple has some of the IP but
Google has some of the IP and ten other
companies there some of the IP and to
the best computer that science knows how
to build can legally not be built in and
the best phone and the best car and the
best medicine and the best every
thing there is because we keep the
actual adaptive knowledge from
synthesizing let alone that everybody is
having to reproduce the same work
because we don't want to share our best
practices and then almost all the budget
is going into marketing against the
other ones rather than actual
development and the marketing is just
lying in manipulation you know at least
about why ours comprehensively better
when they then have to say the same
thing about what their IP does that's
good in our IP does nothing now imagine
if we had a world where all the IP gotta
be synthesized
nobody was dis informing anybody else
nobody was sabotaging anyone else
everyone was an incentive to share all
of the info and to synthesize all the
info to synthesize all of the
intellectual property ideas etc work
towards the best things possible imagine
how much more innovation would actually
be possible how much more collective
intelligence and capacity would actually
be possible
now if our source of adaptive advantage
is that right is we make a world where
and now we have to come back to we were
talking about if you possess a good and
I no longer have access to it were in a
rival risk relationship right you
possessed a piece of information and
that I don't didn't get to have access
to were in Reverse information of
knowledge etc but if you have access to
something and we've structured the
nature of access where we have
engineered the scarcity out of the
system such that you're having access
doesn't make me not have access and you
having access leads to you being a human
who has a full life and some of your
full life is creativity and generativity
and so now not only do you have the full
access to those transportation resources
but also maker studios and art studios
and education and healthcare and all the
kinds of things would make you a healthy
well adaptive creative person and every
well adapted person's creative because
nobody wants to just chill out watching
TV all the time unless they were already
broken broken by a system that tried to
incent them to do that nobody wants
to do or if they can get away out they
will be there broken person but if
someone was supported in an education
system to pay attention to what they
were innately fascinated in and
facilitate that they'll all become
masterful at some things within eight
intrinsic motivation to do those things
and so now in a world where we support
everybody to have access to the things
that they are intrinsically incentive to
want to create which if right now I get
status by having stuff but if we are
engineering secure SEOs system everyone
has access nobody possesses any of it
everybody has access to all but there's
no status of having things as totally
boring there's no differential advantage
the only way you get status the only way
you get to express the uniqueness of who
yours by what you create and so now the
whole system's oriented towards that
they don't create something to get money
because money for what to have access to
she already have access to it but
because you get to be someone who
created that thing in both your own
intrinsic experience evident extras are
they getting to offer to the world will
recognize that so now we have a
situation where we all have access to
Commonwealth resources they create an
anti rivalries relationship to each
other and obviously I'm just speaking
about this at a hundred thousand foot
level and we could drill down on what
the actual architecture looks like but
there's actual architecture here that is
viable that means the designs create
and we have sense-making processes where
we look at what a good design would be
before making a proposition for a design
that don't lead to polarization and
radicalization but that lead to
progressively better synergistic
satisfiers that get us out of theory of
trade-offs and into race and interested
satisfiers also as a way of having
people be more unifying and on the same
team now if I've got this world where
its source of competitive advantage if
you want to call it that is it it is
obsoleted competition within itself so
it has real coherence then not only is
the quality of life they radically
higher because the people don't feel
lonely and they actually have creative
to do and they aren't being used as
instrumental pawns to some other purpose
and etc and the quality of life is
better because they're actually making
better medicine and better technology
and better etc because of the ability
for the IP to synthesize and you know
everything else but this world can also
out in to innovate in really key ways
other places in the world and for then
rather than the rest of the world
wanting to attack it the world it can
actually say here will export solutions
you want and to the rest of world sorts
of creative cause like dependence
relationship then the rest of world says
we want to be able to innovate why
were they able to solve that problem we
weren't able to solve what cooler guys
were like sabotaging each other and
their guys weren't sabotaging each other
we say great here's the social
technology we use now as soon as they
implement that it's not being recognized
that's just the world actually shifting
that's where this model actually becomes
a new basin of Attraction the world
starts flowing - and so you have to do
that you create a prototype of an of a
full-stack civilization that is anti
rivalries it is anti fragile against
rivalry Frank's non power and that is
Otto propagating but by the nature of
the solutions that it is exporting and
by its own adaptive capacity its own
design starts to get implemented other
places and that's ultimately the
designer that is a path to a post
existential risk world which is building
it and prototype in a way we're at Otto
propagates that's so exciting
are there places where these prototypes
are being built kind of but not really
there are intentional communities where
people are
trying to practice some things that they
feel will be relevant a closed-loop
agriculture system right where they at
least have regenerative agriculture and
maybe some kinds of social coherence
technologies where they have a better
system of conflict resolution than our
current judicial system better parenting
better education like we have those
things and those are cool and they're
valuable but they still have to buy
their computers from Apple and fly on a
Boeing to get somewhere that depends
upon environmental destruction war and
so they can't actually provide a
high-tech civilization so then they're
not yet civilization models and the
civilization models are all part of this
one dominant subluxation model so this
is a next endeavor and before a
full-stack civilization occurs obviously
partial ones but that are directed
towards a full-stack civilization have
to occur because in the world we're
talking about there is no place for the
things currency called judges or lawyers
or politicians or bankers because those
systems don't exist now that doesn't
mean that there isn't a equivalent of a
judicial system but it's totally
different from the level of the theory
of ethics to the jurisprudence and
somebody has to be getting trained in
the Civic's of that system and there's
nothing like banking but there are
things like paying attention to how the
accounting of this new economy works but
people have be trained in that I'll give
you one for instance if we think about
the physical economy so we'll take
attention now and just look at physics
we see that there's at least three
different kinds of physics involved in
the materials economy that are
fundamentally different in their math so
there is a physics of atoms physical
atoms there is a physics of energy and
there's the physics of bits and right
now those are all fungible I can use the
same dollar to buy software or to buy
energy or to buy metals or physical
stuff right food but there's a fixed
number of atoms of a certain type on the
planet that are reasonably accessible
and right now we're just taking them
from the environment in a way that
causes depletion and then putting them
back into the environment as wastes and
way the caused accumulation talks to see
on both sides you can't keep doing that
we have to closed-loop it where we have
been a give or take finite amount of
metals and
just medals but hydrocarbons everything
a finite amount of atoms that are in a
closed-loop relationship but it can be
up cycled because we have the energy to
upcycle them which means putting the
same atoms into higher pattern where the
pattern is evolving the pattern stored
in bits so if I take the atoms out of
one battery put it in a new battery
which evolved as battery technology that
new battery is in bits a blueprint and
I'm going to use energy to take the
atoms in the current form disassemble
them and reassemble them into this new
battery and so there's a fixed amount of
atoms we have to close loop those
there's not a fixed amount of energy we
get new energy from the Sun every day
but we have kind of a finite bandwidth
to how much we get so we have to operate
within that's not closed loop right we
can use that up and it has entropy but
within that bandwidth we have to work
and then dips are fundamentally
unlimited limited only by the compute of
the energy and matter
so that can keep you know expanding
basically indefinitely once I've made a
bit I can reproduce it exponentially
without any unit cost because I can
reproduce it exponentially without unit
cost once I've developed it once I can
get exponential returns on software in a
way that I could never get on atomic
stuff which is why Elon has a hard time
raising money for physical stuff and
what's that sold for 19 billion dollars
it's why all the unicorns are software
and mostly social tech or FinTech or
something that is actually doing not
good things for the world but it can
create exponential returns and it's why
Silicon Valley has been basically mostly
just invested in software stuff if you
make those fungible you'll actually be
moving the energy away from the atom and
away from the energy into the virtual
will away from the physical into the
virtual even the virtual depends on the
physical so you're actually debasing the
substrate upon which it depends and so
you notice that since the bit we can
keep having more of forever they don't
go through an entropic degradation when
we use them the energy we can use it
entropically degrades but we get more of
it every day and the atoms don't
entropically degrade but we have to keep
cycling them
there's a fixed number the physics the
accounting of those are totally
different that's not one economy that's
fungible to itself with one accounting
system that's three completely separate
but interacting physical economies and
now again we already said we're not
owning goods we're having access to
shared common wealth services but this
is just first to really go into it it's
a lot of things but these are examples
of some of the considerations that have
to happen to actually be able to think
about things like economics at a level
of depth that is appropriate to the
nature of the issues if we don't answer
the question of what makes a good
civilization and we simply say would
allow civilization to endure and so we
start with let's just say we don't want
excess centralized traffic risk and
there's a whole bunch of different types
of excess and from catastrophic risks
that all have the same generator
functions so we have to create
categorical solutions to the generator
functions it turns out that those are
the generator functions that have made
all the things that we intuitively have
experienced that sucking like violence
and environmental devastation and that
solving those generator functions
doesn't just allow us to survive and
maybe some dystopian dynamic anti rival
risk dynamics with each other and closed
loop dynamics and the proper
relationship between the complicated and
the complex scalable collective
intelligence systems and a right
understanding and theory of choice in
relationship with theory of causation
end up being a way of mapping to a world
that is definitely proto becan any
meaningful definition of proto P and any
meaningful kind of consideration of what
good could mean and so we come back to
this mythopoetic we can't keep going the
way that we're going there's a purgatory
coming and it's gonna go one way or the
other and one way is really fitting one
way is really lovely that's the true
story and Bucky fuller said utopia or
oblivion and it's gonna be hit or miss
til we're actually there when I couldn't
know which which way it goes this the
thing I would just kind of end on is
what it takes if we try to solve the
various risks in isolation is impossible
we fail if what it takes to solve them
categorically ends up also mapping to
how we in
everyone in creating the true the good
and the beautiful that is there to
create progressively better both up
regulating their sense making of what
that is with themselves and with each
other and being able to make that
scaling the collective intelligence that
is progressively answering those
questions better can you leave us with
some book recommendations for anyone who
wants to read up on this a little more
and and expand their understanding books
are are there resources yes I wish I
could share more things than I can but a
lot of what we're thinking in terms of
new civilization design like this has is
new doesn't mean it's not drawing on
lots of elements so a couple things we
mentioned Jeffery West's work scale on
collective intelligence that's very
valuable we talk about some of the
dynamics of game theory that have to
shift and so finite and infinite games
is just my favorite starting point and
it's one of the types of books that is
very simple but has multiple levels of
depth of meaning that if you read it
multiple times you'll be in new insights
yeah that wouldn't blew my mind
yep me too James cars very beautiful and
you know I have a blog civilization
emerging calm that has some articles and
these types of topics and there's also a
book list there with a heap of books
great great awesome this as always is
enlightening and and so fun you know
there are books that are valuable and
there's obviously like all of your
podcasts are valuable if you had the
experience of anything that I said
making sense and actually seeming
obvious but then you also realize you
never thought it in that particular way
and there's a question why did I never
think it in that way even though it
seems obvious after the fact and that's
one of the principles that clarity when
the properties that clarity has is it
can add a novel insight but it seems
obvious and kind of prima facie relates
to everything that you know let me say
okay I wasn't thinking about rival risk
dynamics and upping the ante clearly
enough I wasn't thinking about the
exponential economy in software and
atoms all being fungible like there's a
problem there I wasn't thinking about
open loops closed loops in this
particular way but you can if you start
just asking for yourself what do I think
is actually wrong and
of all the things that seem wrong what
do they have in common and why are those
things that are wrong wrong what is
going on and then go deeper keep going
deeper with that and don't look for one
answer are there a number of different
things that come together that are
partial answers to this and what would
solving that look like and there are
resources of other people's thinking on
these things but they won't replace they
will inspire they won't replace your own
deep thinking on these things for your
own sense making and so the resource
that I would offer the most is when you
are bothered by something where you wish
some beautiful thing existed more than
it does really think hard about why
things are the way they are and know
that the first thought you will come up
with are not that good but if you stop
you won't get beyond there but if you
really keep working on and thinking
about it and then going and researching
in light of that question and then
thinking about it more you actually
start to get novel and meaningful and
deeper sense making that is aligned with
what is yours to pay attention to a
marker to relate to what you said
earlier I think it really helps to use
different modes of inquiry people can
get stuck in just intellectual enquiry
or just spiritual inquiry but you know
all are valuable and when we can see the
same thing from several different
perspectives it becomes a 3d object
rather than just being flat you just
actually mentioned one of my favorite
practices is really endeavoring to see
and experience the world through the
perspective of someone else and actually
see and experience it and if I'm still
thinking no if I was in their position I
wouldn't do that I haven't got it yet so
I was in that position would be if I'm
really putting myself in a position I
would get enraged by the things they're
enraged by I would get excited by the
things are excited by and so this both
has a practice of empathy in connection
as a practice of understanding as a
practice of intelligence and learning
because I see different things if I look
at the world through the lens of a
mechanical engineer I see
everywhere that mechanical engineer see
that you never saw which is different
than if you look through the lens of a
fashion designer where you look through
the lens of you know a game theory
person they're looking at different
things or an evolutionary biologist well
is
the universe that wasn't paying
attention to like when you buy the car
and you see it everywhere you put on the
lens you start seeing all kinds of stuff
your factory sends me but also as a kind
of spiritual technology of getting out
of the default mode of what you think
you are and when I'm trying to be
someone else it's not my personality
that can do that if I'm trying to take
their personality well it's not my
perspective that can do it it is same
consciousness of witnessing my
perspective that can then make me
somebody else's as soon as I do that I
actually dissociate from just being my
personality and then I get some more
spaciousness around it and less reactive
by it and this also relates to not just
looking through the lens of different
personalities or different modern
frameworks it's also looking through the
lens of pre-modern frameworks or even
animal frameworks and that can all be
very useful as well because if we look
at the world through the lens of
quote-unquote primitive tribe then
different things come into focus and
different things become very meaningful
and very powerfully meaningful like it
resonates through your whole being just
you know Wow and that's not to be
dismissed because there's something
there I mean at the very minimum for
self-discovery it's super useful because
you know we spent more time as those
primitive versions of ourselves and we
have the modern versions and you can
kind of untie a lot of behaviors that
you don't really realize you have based
off of just looking at the world from a
primitive standpoint well your air has
some people decide to go visit the
Amazon and live with the tribe and
experience the world through those eyes
and be affected by it and then look at
how they can incorporate elements of
that experience of the world and their
previous experience of the world to
being able to live more fully they'll be
beautiful
I really appreciated being here with you
both and I think I really do want to say
that I love war podcast and I level
you're creating both of you together
it's very easy to have well informed
dystopian beauty and it's easy to not
think about things or it's easy to have
poorly informed positive views but to
have well-informed positive views is
actually tricky because
if we keep being anything like the kinds
of people that we have always been that
do really wonderful and really atrocious
with our power but having
exponentially more power they're all
dystopian scenarios and so we have to be
something really different than we've
ever been which requires some type of
deep shifts that could make that happen
that requires some deep thinking right
in some deep imagination and I know
that's what you are really dedicated to
doing here on the show and minded of
this quote from the book of Romans it
says the pathway to heaven is narrow and
steep and the pathway to hell is wide
and many and it's kind of just like a
way of thinking about thermodynamics
which is that there's just more ways to
break shape than to build it there's
like not that many ways this all the
cells and your body can come together
that make you with the emergent property
of you there's a lot of ways that you
just get like 150 pounds of goo and so
who is they like okay we got a lot of
power and most of those scenarios with a
lot of power suck how could we have this
much power that doesn't suck how could
we have this much power not use it
against each other and we start seeing
Orwell in control systems and we start
seeing how that sucks too and to keep
thinking through how could we have it
that doesn't suck oh and I can't depend
on aliens or Jesus with coming back like
how do we get us to be that kind of
consciousness it's a really good way of
thinking about how to actually address
these problems because if we can't no
Voltaire's without vision man perishes
if we can't even see a well grounded
positive future and positive use of the
technological capacity you have we are
not gonna make it
and so I love that you all have this
space dedicated to exploring I think
incentive is always evil to Mitch so I
don't want to move from perverse
incentive to positive incentive positive
incentive means my sense making has
determined what I think is good and I'm
going to try and extrinsic ly override
your sense making to make a choice
aligned with my sense making I'm gonna
use a extrinsic reward strategy to
co-opt your sovereignty and have your
choice making be based on my sense
making incentive scheme are the neurons
and that is always the basis of evil if
I once have a collective intelligence
that's actually intelligent I need
everyone to have intrinsic sense making
and choice making that is uncorruptible
which means it's not being co-opted by
extrinsic reward and Punishment schemas
I got this wrong at first I used to say
we have to create a world where the
incentive of every agent is rigorously
aligned with the well-being of every
other agent and of the Commons that is
wrong what is right is to say that we
must rigorously remove any place where
the incentive of an agent is misaligned
with the well-being of other agents in
the Commons but a adequate future is one
that has no system of structural
incentive that's a mind-blower the cells
in your body are actually not trying to
get the other ones to do what they want
them to do they have their own internal
sense making processes and they do what
makes sense to them and what makes sense
them also happens to be what's good for
the ones around them because they depend
on the ones around them and vice versa
and they're in a communication process
but the brain is not overriding the
salesmen and in no way could handle the
complexity necessary of the cells not
doing their own sense making and so
better incentive schemas as a transition
which is happening in the blockchain is
nice
it's worse than more births incentives
but it is transitional not post
transitional it actually does not
address existential risk it doesn't give
us the right collective intelligence the
right collective intelligence has to be
fractal sovereignty meaning at the level
of an individual and every group size it
has its own intact sense making in
choice making it ends up being vectoring
towards Omni consideration the level of
that we're talking about is hard to
imagine yeah and what has to be invented
to even begin a transition and then be
put to rest so that the next version can
come along is such a long road the
reason that we incent people is because
we have a civilization that needs a lot
of done that is not fun
it's dreadful stuff
we want to get the people to do the
dreadful stuff if we created a
Commonwealth River and had access to
resources then nobody would do the
dreadful stuff and so then the state
would have to force them that's why we
don't like communism then you get the
state imperialism so we say okay cool
we'll let the free market force them
instead it's the economic servitude but
at least that doesn't look like somebody
did it because the market is the just
anonymous thing right if you don't do
the shitty job you're homeless and your
kids can't eat cool but we'll tell you
the story that you can work your way up
and you know become wealthy even though
statistically we know that it's silly it
happened to those two guys that one time
even though statistically the rest of
the time having more resources makes it
easier to make more resources and having
less resources makes it harder to make
more resources into the system as a
gradient it makes it actually continue
in the direction of inequality not that
you know otherwise but so that's where
incentive came from right was that's the
good side at the negative side is a few
controlling of many one to use incentive
reward and punishment and to get people
to do the shitty things we have to do
that this is using choice to create a
system of causation incentive as a
causal system game theory as a causal
system to control the choice of others
controller co-op I want to have my
theory of choice effect causal dynamics
that are only causal ie
if I make an automated robot I haven't
actually made a sentient being a utility
so I'm gonna say something even deeper
which is instrumental relationships are
evil can you expand that yeah I'm
interacting with you to meet some people
that you know to get my network ahead or
to get some knowledge from you or to
gain access to something or to whatever
it is I have something that I want to do
that you are an instrument towards
you're a path towards to utilitarian
ethic then you are a into a means for me
so however I relate with you however it
affects your own sovereign sentient
experience is a place I might
externalize harm because it's not why
I'm relating with you yeah yeah
and so in a healthy world world of the
future other people need to have
intrinsic value independent of
utilitarian value to everyone that's a
part of the culture and not just the
other people and other beings all kinds
of sentient beings but relationships
have intrinsic values so I'm gonna
invest in the integrity of our
relationship independent of me getting
anything out of it because it is
actually the basis of meaningfulness
itself which is why in a utilitarian and
instrumental dynamic we're getting ahead
while feeling utterly
meaningless and destroying everything
that is meaningful in the process that
is us being hooked to addiction to a
stupid game where what we think we want
is not not what we actually want and
what we think of as a win is actually a
Omni stupid thing and this is why you
know like the the Hindu concept of
Dharma was a virtue ethics not a
utilitarian ethic and and there was a
very meaningful set of concepts if do
what is inherently right in your
relationship with life independent of
what the outcome might be because you
really don't know what the
outcome is gonna be and if you try and
just figure out the outcome is gonna be
you're gonna be wrong a lot of times and
you're also gonna justify a lot of
unethical styles and utilitarianism is
kind of the rampant ethics that anyone
who's paying attention to ethics pays
attention to right now and it's not
without any merit but it is also
problematic it is up there with
democracy and capitalism you know in the
philosophy of science in terms of being
a problematic thing to be the dominant
system because we cannot actually
predict and complex systems well enough
to do a utilitarian thing and they
intrinsic dynamics of a relationship and
another being in that becoming moved to
being a means to an end other than them
and as soon as I start factoring
everything meaningful along the chain of
whatever I think my howcome is to where
my outcome is actually being in a way
that is an integrity with an honoring of
all life now it's the virtue of it yeah
I I was having this conversation
recently
about people who are obsessed with life
hacking and optimizing everything and
when they get into that mindset
eventually they get to what what they
call optimizing relationships and then
they start putting people on a value
hierarchy where they want to interact
with high-value people and they want to
get a high value woman and they're using
these tactics to find and attract the
most high-value woman and it's funny
because those people in my experience
are some of the most existentially
unhappy people that I've met and they
will never demonstrate it outward in an
outward way but that's what I've noticed
that you know people who try to optimize
everything in this kind of utilitarian
way end up really profoundly unhappy
yeah what's the same thing as
continuously pursuing a better hi it's
I'm getting a hit from winning at a
particular thing so I got to try and win
at it all the time
but I need the hit because my baseline
is the lay feels meaningless
because I don't actually have any real
relationships and there I don't even
know what meaning needs I don't even
know what intimacy means and so that
hypo normal environment needs a hyper
normal stimuli to feel anything and then
the fact that I used people
instrumentally has people end up not
liking me which makes me hurt even more
which makes me want another hit II
people like you make it super DC you
just come on and it's like we listen to
audiobooks all day and then we get to
actually talk to the person who is
coming up with the cutting-edge ideas
themselves so it's quite interesting
Thank You y'all it's always wonderful
getting our brains blown by you thank
you thank you both this is really fun
all right that's it thanks for listening
guys that was the last part of our
fascinating conversation with Daniel
schmuck John Berger if you haven't heard
the first and second part of this
interview you can find it at future
thinkers our org slash 57 you can also
find all the links and resources
mentioned in all three episodes there
and to check out our sponsor qual yet go
to future thinkers org slash brain hat
if you're new to the show and you like a
list of our top episodes and resources
go to future thinkers org slash start if
you want to sponsor our show go to
future thinkers that org
laughs sponsor if you liked our podcast
leave us a rating and a review on iTunes
and elsewhere it helps others find the
show and we really appreciate it
thanks for listening and we'll see you
in the next episode
[Music]